<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvedding sermon preached at Bentley in Darby-shire vpon Michaelmasse day last past anno Domini. 1607. Wherein is set forth the bond and preseruation. ... By R. Abbot ...</title>
            <author>Abbot, Robert, 1560-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 55</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100549</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836386</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836386</idno>
            <idno type="VID">654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1163:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvedding sermon preached at Bentley in Darby-shire vpon Michaelmasse day last past anno Domini. 1607. Wherein is set forth the bond and preseruation. ... By R. Abbot ...</title>
                  <author>Abbot, Robert, 1560-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 67, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By N. O[kes] for Roger Iackson dwelling in Fleetstreet neere to the great conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At the wedding of Sir John Stanhope and Olive Berrisford.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The three final leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wedding sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:654:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VVEDDING SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT BENTLEY in Darby-ſhire, vpon Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe day laſt paſt Anno Domini. 1607.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS SET FORTH the Bond and Preſeruation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The ſpirituall coniunction betwixt God and man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Corporall marriage betwixt man and vvoman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>The neighbourly ſocietie betwixt man and man.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. ABBOT <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>N. O.</hi> for Roger Iack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon dwelling in Fleetſtreet neere to the great Conduit. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:654:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:654:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir <hi>John Stanhope</hi> Knight, the Father of the bridegroome Knight, my <hi>moſt louing and good Patron.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull Knight my verie good Patron, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I made a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of vſing your name, for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of ſo ſmall a matter as this ſermon is; yet I eaſily reſolued that ſith it had pleaſed you to craue the copy thereof, you would pardon mee to grace it with the dedication. I
<pb facs="tcp:654:3"/> might wel doubt to offer ſo little wher I owe ſo much, but that I conſidered that ſmall offices ſometimes are teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of great affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; preſumed that according to your wonted loue, you would take the wil in good worth, howſoeuer the worke ſeeme to bee of ſmall import. Accept it therefore I humbly pray you, as a very thankfull acknowledgement of your great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towards mee, both in calling me, firſt to the place where now I liue, and giuing me ſince ſuch reſpect and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as whereby I haue with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and contentment enioyed the ſame. And ſurely if therein I haue done in publicke any profitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to the Church of God, a great part thereof is to bee reputed to you, who ſo freely and graciouſly of your owne voluntary accord, and onely for the workes ſake which I perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, being my ſelfe wholy ſtrange and vnknowne to you, vouchſafed by
<pb facs="tcp:654:3"/> your gift to free mee of that inceſſant labour wherein I had beene imployed before, for the ſpace of tenne yeares in reading and preaching in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church and Citie of Worceſtor, and to ſetle mee in a place, where I might more freely diſpoſe of my ſelfe, though not to withdraw my ſelfe from the ſeruice to which I had deuoted my ſelfe, yet in ſome part to beſtow my time to the common benefit of the whole Church, which before was limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to one onely congregation. Amidst which imployments, either publicke or priuate, if I attaine to doe any thing to yeeld you any helpe or furtherance in things appertaining to God, and in Gods behalfe to anſwer the end wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at you aimed in your firſt acceptance of me, I much reioyce therein, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal reioyce, and thinke that houre or time happily bestowed, wherein I ſhall be <hi>the helper of your ioy,</hi> and<note place="margin">2. Co 1. 24</note> of that faith wherby you ſhall ſtand in
<pb facs="tcp:654:4"/> the day of the Lord Ieſus. As for this ſermon, being but a countrey exerciſe, if any ſhall thinke it not ſo well po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed as that it ſhould bee fit in this ſort to goe abroad, your approbation ſhall be my excuſe, and in that nature I commend it to you that haue deſired it, wiſhing with it to you, and to your whole houſe, all happines and honour, and that the Oliue by my ſeruice im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted into your ſtocke, may yeeld many branches, to the enlarging and ſtrengthning thereof, ſo reſting al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all dutie, much bounden and deuoted, R. Abbot.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:654:4"/>
            <head>A WEDDING SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON PREACHED AT the mariage of Sir <hi>Iohn Stanhope</hi> Knight, ſecond ſon to the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir <hi>Iohn Stanhope</hi> Knight of <hi>Eluaſton in the ſame County to Mistres</hi> Oliue Berrisford, now the Ladie Oliue Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope, ſole daughter and heire to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Edward Berrisford of Berriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Amos 3. 3.</bibl>
               <q>Can two walke together except they bee agreed?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words are but few, yet fewe as they are, doe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter matter of a large diſcourſe, of the bond and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of ſpirituall amitie and coniunction betwixt GOD and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: of corporall marriage betwixt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:654:5"/> man and woman, and of neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacietie betwixt man and man. The locall vſe and application of the words is to ſhew a iuſt reaſon of Gods withdrawing himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to whome he ſpeaketh, and therefore they giue vs occaſion principally to conſider what is the occaſion of breach betwixt GOD and vs. But the ſame reaſon being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the affections &amp; diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of men in ſorting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues one with another, do lead vs alſo to conſider wherein ſtandeth either the maintenance or the breach &amp; diſunion of thoſe coniunctions &amp; ſocieties which god hath ordeined amongſt vs. The Prophet hauing in the firſt verſe of the chapter cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the children of Iſrael to heare the word of the Lord,</hi> propoundeth to them in the ſecond verſe to call to minde the great loue and mercie wherewith hee had reſpected &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:654:5"/> honoured them aboue al the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth. <hi>You onely haue I knowne, ſaith the Lord, of all the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the earth.</hi> Where by <hi>knowing</hi> he meaneth acording to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe, the taking knowledge of them in ſpeciall loue and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be their God &amp; to do them good; when as hee paſſed by other nations <hi>as a stranger,</hi> as if hee had no reſpect or regard vnto them. Now wheras the conſideration of this great mercie ſhould haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all thankfulneſſe &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards God, they contrariwiſe <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 5. 4. 7.</note>, <hi>in ſteede of grapes brought forth wilde grapes; for iudgement &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, oppreſſion and cruelty,</hi> ſo as that they ſeemed nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know or regard him who had ſo graciouſly of his owne meere and voluntarie loue accepted them. Hereupon the Prophet addeth, <hi>Therfore I will viſit you for all your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:654:6"/> iniquities, ſaith the Lord,</hi> implying herein that rule of iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding which our ſauiour Chriſt ſetteth downe as a thing certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined with GOD; <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 12. 48</note> 
               <hi>To whomſoeuer much is giuen, of him much ſhalbe required:</hi> the greater mercie, the greater iudgement; the higher the place, the more dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fall: <note n="c" place="margin">Bernard. in cant. ſer. 84.</note> 
               <hi>they,</hi> ſaith Bernard, <hi>who for grace receiued ſeemed to be the greatest, for not beeing gratefull become of least reckoning with God.</hi> In effect therefore hee ſaith vnto them, as ye haue beene beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſo ye ſhalbe moſt greeuouſly &amp; ſeuerely puniſhed: ſomewhat may in equitie bee remitted to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but all ſhalbe required of you; I <hi>wil viſite you for all your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And that it might not ſeeme ſtrange vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he who had vndertaken <note n="d" place="margin">Leuit. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>to dwell amongſt them, and to walke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:654:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with them,</hi> ſhould thus caſt them off &amp; leaue their company; in the words which I haue propoſed, he appealeth to themſelues and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them Iudges whether his doing therein bee any other but what they themſelues out of their owne conuerſation muſt needes iuſtify and make good. <hi>Can two</hi> or <hi>wil two walke together except they be agreed?</hi> Will any two of you ſort your ſelues to conuerſe &amp; liue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether who haue no accord or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grement each with other? It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to haue company on the way, and there is comfort in it; but will any man be companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him by whom he is continually thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prouoked? Doth not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of you make choice of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as wherewith he may liue at quietnes and peace? How can you then expect to haue me to walke with you when as there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:654:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> or agreement betwixt you and me? I call one way: you turne wilfully another way: I command one thing and you do the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. You prouoke me with your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities from day to day. Therfore be ye wel aſſured that your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is not for me, neither wil I haue any ſociety or felowſhip with you.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The terme of <hi>walking</hi> as it is referred to God, betokeneth his gratious &amp; healthfull preſence as it is applied to men, it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the conuerſation and life of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To make vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the words, wee may here obſerue firſt the life of man compared to a <hi>walke.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly wee are to note wherein ſtandeth the commoditie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencie of this walke, and that is to <hi>walke together,</hi> in ſocietie and company. Thirdly what is the means to hold vs together; which is concord and agreement. Of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:654:7"/> the firſt we haue example in thoſe exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the apoſtle, <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 13 13.</note> 
               <hi>Walke honeſtly as in the day time:</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eph, 5. 8. <hi>Ibid. ver. 15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>walke as children of light,</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Th. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>walke circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly not as vnwiſe but as wiſe:</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">h</hi> 
               <hi>walke worthy of him who hath called you into his kingdome and glory.</hi> But what ſhould I need to bring many exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of that which in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is ſo commonly and euerie where to be found? let vs rather conſider what is to bee gathered thereof for our inſtruction. <hi>A walke</hi> therefore importeth, firſt <hi>a way</hi> wherein wee are to walke: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly an <hi>end</hi> whereto we walke: thirdly <hi>motion</hi> in the way; and fourthly <hi>proceeding or going for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward therein,</hi> &amp; laſtly <hi>perſeuerance and continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> vnto the waies end, what our <hi>way</hi> for our walke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſignifieth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi rend="sup">i</hi> 
               <hi>bleſſed are they that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 1.</note> 
               <hi>in the way,</hi> and addeth by way
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:654:8"/> of expoſition, <hi>which walk in the law of the lord. The law of the Lord</hi> is the way wherin we are to walke. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Moſes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had giuen the law of God to the people of Iſrael biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 5. 33.</note> 
               <hi>to walke in al that way which the lord their God had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And hence are thoſe phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <note n="l" place="margin">Ex. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 8. Deut. 9. 12.</note> 
               <hi>turning out of the way,</hi> when we forſake the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of God, and <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 34.</note> 
               <hi>keeping his way</hi> when we obſerue the ſame. It is a great queſtion in our dayes, what way it is wherin we may ſafely &amp; ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walke, &amp; many are much diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted &amp; perplexed hereabout, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee ſo great contention and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie which is the right way. But all this doubt God him ſelfe reſolueth, to them that are willing to take reſolution of him; the law of the Lord, the word of God which hee hath deliuered to vs by his Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:654:8"/> that onely is the ſure and certaine way. Hee that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth according to this law, hee teacheth the right way: hee that teacheth beſide this law, ſeeme he to be of neuer ſo great authoritie and credit, hee teacheth a wrong way. In this way God hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs, all the waies which he will haue vs to goe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and how to liue; what to doe, and what to eſchew; and not onely of ſuch duties as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, but alſo what concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery man in his ſpecial ſtate and calling; what is the dutie both of Prince and ſubiect, of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour and of the fiocke, of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the wife, the Parents and the children, the Maſter and the ſeruants, the rich &amp; the poore, the high and the low; the word of God according to the phraſe of our Sauiour Chriſt, <note n="n" place="margin">Mar. 13. 24.</note> 
               <hi>appointeth to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:654:9"/> euery man his worke,</hi> to euery man that ſeruice that his maſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Gregor. Moral<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> li. 16. cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>By the Scripture,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of Rome, <hi>God telleth vs all his will;</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ibid. li. 18. ca. 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſo that if men will ſpeake truly, they muſt from thence receiue that which they will ſpeake;</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. de. vtil. cre dendi. ca. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the doctrine whereof is ſo framed,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Austine, as that there is no man but may draw from thence that that is ſufficient for him, if hee come with deuotion and piety to draw, as true religion requireth hee ſhould doe;</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Hieron. in Pſal. 86.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the Princes of the Church,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> meaning the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>did ſo write, as that not a few onely, but all ſhould vnderstand;</hi> ſo as that the ſcripture, as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>is</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gregor. ad Leand. epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. in lib. Mor. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>a ſtreame wherein both the Elephant may ſwimme, and alſo the Lambe may wade;</hi> yee ſo as that <note n="t" place="margin">Origen. cont. Celſ. lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>in one and the ſame text,</hi> as <hi>Orig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, <hi>many times are found tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:654:9"/> together both the things which ſerue for the exerciſing of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and which miniſter edification to to the more weake and ſimple.</hi> In the Scripture wee ſhall find that way whereof the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth when hee ſaith; <note n="u" place="margin">Ier. 6. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Stand vpon the waies and behold, and aske for the old way which is the good way, and walke therin, and ye ſhall find rest for your ſoules.</hi> Wherby he inſtructed the people to take view of the waies of their forefathers, and thence to make choice, not of that way which their latter fathers taught them, of which elſewhere they are warned, <note n="x" place="margin">Ezec. 20. 18.</note> 
               <hi>VValke ye not in the ordinances of your fathers, neither obſerue their manners;</hi> but of that wherein the Patriarches and firſt fathers walked, who receiued the ſame from God, and by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God left the ſame recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a memoriall to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:654:10"/> A fooliſh terme there is vſed by many ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſons amongſt vs of the <hi>old law, the old Religion,</hi> by which they vnderſtand the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Poperie, as if popery were the old religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe ſome ages paſt haue followed it, and bin abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therby. Indeed the Scribes and Phariſies for the very ſame cauſe called their traditions <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 5. 21 27. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the old</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but the true old religion is of ancienter continuance, euen that way which the Patriarches &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Euangeliſts &amp; Apoſtles haue traced out, and directed vnto vs, hauing themſelues learned it from God, &amp; by the reuelation of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; by his appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t left the ſame recorded in ſcripture to our vſe. Of this it is that the paſtours &amp; teachers of the church are inſtructed to ſay to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <note n="z" place="margin">Eſai. 30. 21.</note> 
               <hi>This is the way, walke in the ſame, when thou turneſt to the right
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:654:10"/> hand, or when thou turnest to the left.</hi> Chriſt is the directour of this way: of him the father hath ſaid, <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 17. 5</note> 
               <hi>Heare him;</hi> and therefore <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> inferreth; <note n="b" place="margin">Cyprian. lib. 2. epiſt. 3.</note> 
               <hi>If Chriſt onely be to be heard or harkened vnto, we are not to regard what any man before vs hath thought fit to be done, but what Christ hath done, who is before all: for we are not to follow the cuſtome of men, but the truth of God.</hi> And if by this rule we eſteeme of the way wee ſhall ſoone perceiue that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is out of the way, becauſe in that path which the Apoſtles and Prophets haue chalked out vnto vs, we neither find the Pope, nor his pardons, nor his maſſe, nor his images, nor his reliques; yea all theſe and the reſt of his trinkets, are eaſily perceiued to be but falſe and baſe, and broken wares.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If wee deſire ſomwhat more briefly to heare the way, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:654:11"/> Chriſt telleth vs, <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 14 6.</note> 
               <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life: no man cometh to the father but by me.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth the words, <note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioan. tract. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Ambulare vis? &amp;c. Art thou deſirous to walke? I am the way. Woldeſt thou not be deceiued? I am the truth. Woldeſt thou not die? I am the life. There is no whither for thee to go but to me: there is no way for thee to go by but by me.</hi> Chriſt only him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is our way to come to Chriſt, <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 10. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Through the vaile,</hi> that is, <hi>his fleſh he hath prepared the new and liuing way whereby we are to enter into the holy place.</hi> His paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on is our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our righteouſnes, his reſurrection our iuſtification; he is for vs whatſoeuer wee neede to bring vs vnto God. <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 4 12.</note> 
               <hi>There is not ſaluation in any other, nor any other name giuen vnder heauen by which we muſt be ſaued.</hi> This way muſt we go, if we will go the right way: but if wee ſeeke for a way in our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:654:11"/> ſelues or in any other creature; if we <note n="g" place="margin">Ro. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſet vp our owne righteouſnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the righteouſnes of God:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother altar and ſacrifice againſt the croſſe and ſacrifice of Chriſt; if we truſt to other mediations &amp; merits and ſatisfactions, wee are out of the way; wee wander in ſtrange and crooked paths, which will neuer bring vs to our deſired end. In a word, the Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to inſtruct vs of the rightway, and to that purpoſe ſetting downe a briefe ſumme of the doctrine of the goſpell ſaith thus, <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>God forbid that I ſhould reioice but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: wherby the world is crucified vnto me, and I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: for in Christ Ieſus nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion auaileth any thing, nor vncircumciſion but a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Now hereto he addeth; <hi>And they that walk according to this rule, peace and mercie ſhall be vpon them.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:654:12"/> Here is then the rule and way of our walke, to reioice, that is, to put truſt and confidence of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes &amp; ſaluation only in the croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, not in the croſſe of <hi>Peter,</hi> or in the croſſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> or of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but only in the croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; ſo to be poſſeſſed with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, as for the enioying of the ioy hereof to bee mortified to all worldly conuerſation, and to be content to beare the malice and perſecution of the world. They that walke in this way and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this rule, they ſhall finde mercie with GOD to attaine to peace; but with the reſt it ſhall come to paſſe which <hi>Ionas</hi> ſaith: <note n="i" place="margin">Ionas. 2. 8</note> 
               <hi>They that wait vpon lying vanities, forſake their owne mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Now that <hi>peace</hi> is the end of our walke, euen the ending of all our labours and ſorrowes, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:654:12"/> fruition &amp; enioying of God, who is <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 15. 33.</note> 
               <hi>the GOD of peace,</hi> and of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, who is <note n="l" place="margin">Eſai. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the Prince of peace,</hi> in whom is full &amp; perfect bliſſe and happines for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. This is the thing wherto all our walking ought to tend, which as the marke before the archer, ſo ought to be before our eies to aime at in al the courſe of our life, and the regard thereof ſo to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all other regards, as that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be further or otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded then as may ſtand with the attaining of this end, hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that which our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith: <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 16. 26.</note> 
               <hi>what profiteth it a man to winne the whole world and to loſe his owne ſoule?</hi> This mind the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth when he ſaith, <note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>I haue counted all things loſſe for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I haue counted all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:654:13"/> things loſſe, and doe iudge them to be dung that I might winne Chriſt &amp;c. that I may know him &amp; the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his reſurrection, and the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his afflictions, and be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his death, if by any means I may attaine to the reſurrection of the dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Giue me hunger &amp; thirſt, cold and nakednes, ſickneſſe and ſores, torment and death, this end to attaine to the bleſſed reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead maketh amends for all. Giue me the kingdomes of the earth and all the pleaſures and glory thereof, yet if my end be not to attaine this end, I am a moſt wretched man, and better had it beene for me that I had neuer bin borne. The more may we wonder at the ſtrange retchleſneſſe of the greateſt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of men, with whom this is leaſt of all thought of, and leaſt of all reſpected, <note n="o" place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnard.</note> 
               <hi>ſo vainley v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their ſoules,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:654:13"/> as if they did not reckon that they haue any ſoules at all;</hi> ſo wholly dreaming and doating vpon the things of the world, as if they were borne to no other end but to liue for euer in the world. A wandring fancy men commonly haue of a deſire to come to heauen, but how few ſet their hearts thereupon to make it the drift of their life, the main end of all their purpoſes and counſels, and doe not rather drowne the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereof in the purpoſes and deſires of other things? That we runne not with others into this common errour, let vs duely reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that our life is but a walke, and a walke muſt haue an end, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it concerneth vs ſo to frame our courſes and doings, as that we may make a good end, that our death to this world may be to vs the beginning of euerlaſting life in the world to come.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:654:14"/>5 To this end we are to call to minde that <hi>walking</hi> importeth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and ſtirring, and therfore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſeth vs, that ſeeing our life is a <hi>walke,</hi> we are ſtill to be mouing and ſtirring and doing in the way and worke of God: that being by the mercy of God broght into the right way, we are not there to ſit downe at reſt, idle and vnfruitfull, but as the life of Chriſt is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 10, 38.</note> 
               <hi>He vvent about doing good,</hi> ſo ought our walking and life bee to doe good, to glorifie God, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of God and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, to further righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and truth, to helpe the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and afflicted, to comfort the comfortles, to releeue the widow and fatherles, and to theſe ends to doe all other good workes which either the common duety of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity or our own priuate calling requireth of vs. <hi>Titus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:654:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Rome when he had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed a day wherein he had done no ſpeciall good deede, no good turne to any man, was wont to ſay: <hi>Diemperdidi, I haue loſt a day.</hi> Alas, what a thing is it when a Chriſtian man ſhall ſo ſpend a whole life as that in the end thereof hee may ſay, <hi>Vitam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi; I haue loſt a life:</hi> I haue liued ſo as that I haue neither done any faithfull ſeruice to God, nor left any memoriall or example of any good that I haue done amongſt men! <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith well, that <note n="q" place="margin">Seneca de tranquil. animi.</note> 
               <hi>there is nothing more ſhamefull then an old man who hath no other argument to proue that he hath liued long but onely that he is old;</hi> no good fruits, no good effects, by which it may be remembred that his life from time to time hath bene benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to other men. Euen ſo it is: a long life is but a great reproch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:654:15"/> when by weldoing it hath left no teſtimonie of it ſelfe. To which purpoſe it is worth the noting which <hi>Gregory</hi> obſerueth, that of good men it is ſayd in Scripture, that ſuch a one or ſuch a one died old and <note n="r" place="margin">Greg. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. l. 35. cap. 15.</note> 
               <hi>full of dayes,</hi> but neuer of an euill man; as whereby wee ſhould vnderſtand that he is <hi>full of dayes,</hi> who hath made good vſe of his dayes and beſtowed them in good deeds; but otherwiſe we do but loſe our dayes, and by loſing our dayes looſe our ſelues alſo. He that hath warned vs that we ſhall <note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 12. 36.</note> 
               <hi>giue account of our idle words,</hi> doth thereby aduertiſe vs that we ſhall giue account of our idle houres; and much more of our dayes, and moneths, and yeares, which ſo many of vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow wholly in a manner in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and vanity, in riotouſneſſe and vnthriftineſſe, in ſinne and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:654:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> wickedneſſe, and therefore when they come to their end lye tumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in their ſickneſſe, <note n="t" place="margin">Eſay 51. 20.</note> 
               <hi>like a wild bull in a net,</hi> as the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>full of the wrath of the Lord,</hi> without any hope, without any comfort, becauſe their life hath bene ſuch as hath yeelded them no hope or comfort towards God. Bleſſed is he who when the ſummons of death commeth, <hi>ſet thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die,</hi> can ſay to God as <hi>Ezechias</hi> did, <note n="u" place="margin">Eſay 38. 3.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord I haue walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 But this <hi>walking</hi> importeth not only mouing and ſtirring, but mouing and going forward, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we gain the way more &amp; more and come neerer and neerer to the end. Euen ſo are we ſtill to be gaining, and growing, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward in the wayes of God in all vertue and goodnes; not to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:654:16"/> ſtand ſtill at one ſtay, and as it were to runne in one ring, but as wee labour to thriue in the goods of this world, ſo much more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in thoſe things, whereby we may be <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> 
               <hi>rich in God,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 84. 7.</note> 
               <hi>To goe from ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ro. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>from faith to faith,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>from glory to glory;</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>to grow in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauior Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Thus doth <hi>Solomon</hi> inſtruct vs that <note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 4. 18.</note> 
               <hi>the way of the righteous ſhineth as the light which ſhineth more and more vnto the perfect day.</hi> Which he that careth not to doe, is as the man that ſpendeth of the ſtocke, and groweth thereby to decay: for <note n="d" place="margin">Gregor. in Paſtoral. par. 3. admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nit. 35.</note>, <hi>the ſoule of man in this world is like vnto a ſhip or boate,</hi> as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>going againſt the ſtream, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not reſt in one place, but by the ſway of the water is caried downeward, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse it be ſtill labouring to go vpward.</hi> Therfore <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith; <note n="e" place="margin">Bernard. in purific. ſer. 3</note> 
               <hi>Not to go
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:654:16"/> forward in the way of life is to go back<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward;</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem epiſt.</hi> 2 53.</note> 
               <hi>not to care to increaſe, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Idem epiſt. 91.</note> 
               <hi>look where thou beginneſt not to regard to grow better, there thou quite giueſt ouer to be good at all.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. Apoſt. ſer. 15.</note> 
               <hi>If thou ſay, I haue enough,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, thou art gone, thou art vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Laſtly this growth requireth perſeuerance &amp; continuance till we come to the end whereto our walking is directed. The end is all in all; to giue ouer before we come to the end, though it be but in the laſt attempt, is the loſſe of all our labour and reward. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſo run,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, that ye may obtaine;</hi> which is, <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 3. 14</note> 
               <hi>when we keepe ſure vnto the end that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wherwith we are vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> that is, hold faſt to the end the true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and faith of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we firſt began, and is a ſure foundation for vs to build vpon;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:654:17"/> for <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 24. 13.</note> 
               <hi>hee that continueth to the end,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>he ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Many begin in the ſpirit, and ſeeme for the time to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſpirit, and yet afterward end in the fleſh, and <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 6. 8.</note> 
               <hi>of the fleſh reape corruption.</hi> Many <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 9. 2.</note> 
               <hi>lay their hand to the plough, and afterwards looke back,</hi> and thereby <hi>are vnfit for the kingdome of God.</hi> Therefore let vs hearken to Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">2. Iohn verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed to your ſelues that wee loſe not the things that we haue done, but that we may receiue a great reward.</hi> We loſe the things that we haue done when we growe weary of doing them; <note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 6. 9.</note> 
               <hi>weary of well doing,</hi> and leaue to go forward in that courſe wherein we haue well begun. And thus much of the life of man ſet forth vnto vs by a walke.</p>
            <p n="8">8 It followeth now that we ſpeake of the conueniencie of this <hi>walke,</hi> which ſtandeth in <hi>walking
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:654:17"/> together,</hi> in company and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which as the Prophets words leade vs to conſider, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth firſt at two; as we find accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the firſt ſocietie to haue bene betwixt two, God and Man; and the ſecond betwixt two, Man and Woman: From whence ſpring all other ſocieties which God hath ordeined for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe of the life of man. God made man of the duſt of the earth, that from the earth he might haue company to dwell with him in heauen; but yet ſo as that firſt he would walke with man, and would haue man to walke together with God here vpon earth. Which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of walking with God, and of care to haue God to walke with vs, though on our part it began but in one, yet is now belonging to vs all who are of that one, who either ſeuerally or ioyntly ought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:654:18"/> to make it our happines and bliſſe to enioy this gracious amity and friendſhip with God. Which mind the Prophet teacheth vs to put on, when hee ſo often ſaith: <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 33 12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord, and bleſſed are they whom he hath choſen to him to be his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſa. 144 15.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they who haue the Lord for their God:</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 146. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that hath the God of</hi> Iacob <hi>for his helpe, and whoſe hope is in the Lord his God.</hi> The reaſon whereof the Apoſtle teacheth vs when he ſaith: <note n="t" place="margin">Ro. 8. 31.</note> 
               <hi>If God be with vs,</hi> or <hi>on our ſide, who can be againſt vs?</hi> Be it that in wil and purpoſe they be againſt vs, yet in act and deed they can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect nothing. Which made the Prophet when he had but named <note n="u" place="margin">Eſay 8. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Immanuel, God with vs,</hi> to breake out into thoſe words of defiance, <hi>Girde your ſelues, and ye ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in peeces; girde your ſelues, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:654:18"/> yee ſhall be broken in peeces; take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell together, and it ſhall come to nought; pronounce a decree, and it ſhall not ſtand; for God is with vs.</hi> Thus the people of God reioyce in the Pſalme, <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 46. 1</note> 
               <hi>God is our hope and ſtrength, a very preſent helpe in trouble; therefore will we not feare though the earth be moued, and though the hils be caried into the midst of the ſea, though the waters thereof rage and ſwell, and though the mountaines ſhake at the tempeſt of the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Lord of hosts is with vs, the God of</hi> Iacob <hi>is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> is full of theſe meditations: <note n="y" place="margin">Pſa. 27. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is my light and my ſaluation; whom then ſhall I feare? the Lord is the ſtrength of my life; of whom then ſhall I be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid?</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſa. 62. 6. 7.</note> 
               <hi>God is my ſtrength and my ſaluation; he is my defence; I ſhall not be remoued; in God is my health and my glory, the rocke of my might; in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:654:19"/> God is my truſt.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Whom haue I in heauen but thee, and what do I deſire vpon earth in compariſon of thee? my fleſh and my heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my life, and my portion for euer.</hi> Herein ſtandeth the ioy and contentment of the godly poore man, that though he want the wealth and glory of the world, yet he hath the grace of God, he walketh with God, and hath God to walke with him; which though it cary no ſhew to the world, yet he more eſteemeth thereof then of all the wealth of the whole world. And without this, what is all the pompe and glory of the world? though a man haue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the world can yeeld him, yet what is it all without God? The rich man in the Goſpell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth in the abundance of his goods; he ſaith to his ſoule, <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 12. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Soule, eate, drinke, take thy pleaſure; thou
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:654:19"/> haſt goods layd vp in ſtore for many yeares.</hi> But it was anſwered to him from aboue, <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall they take away thy ſoule from thee; and then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou doeſt poſseſſe? ſo is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>that is rich in this world and is not rich in God.</hi> He is a foole by the teſtimony of our Sauiour Chriſt, who ioyeth to be rich in the goods of this world, and neglecteth to be rich towards God, rich in knowledge, rich in faith, rich in grace, rich in good workes, rich in all things whereby we ſhould be fitted and prepared, <note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>to the rich and glorious inheritance of the ſaints of God.</hi> In a word, <hi>the life of the body is the ſoule, and the life of the ſoule is God;</hi> and as the body dieth in the departure of the ſoule; ſo is the ſoule, yea the whole man dead when he is left of God.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:654:20"/> Without God what is all our life but a ſhadow, which ſheweth to be ſomething, and indeede is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? what, but a dreame, which mocketh a man, and maketh him beleeue that he is a king, when he is but a peaſant; that he is rich and abounding in treaſure, when he is a very beggar; <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 29. 8.</note> that he is well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed at a goodly banquet, when he is readie to die for hunger. He ſaith afterwards, Me thought it was thus and thus; but he findeth it nothing ſo. Euen ſo the glory of worldly ſtate flattereth men and perſwadeth them that they are the only fortunate and happy men, when indeede being ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to God and deuoide of his grace, they are found in the end to be moſt wretched and vnhappie of all other. <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 49. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Their beautie is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med when they are caried from their houſes to their graues;</hi> death ſtaineth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:654:20"/> the pride of all their glory, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Beere it is written as to <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſar</hi> vpon the wall: <note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 5. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Mene: God hath numbred thy kingdome, and hath finiſhed it;</hi> thou haſt henceforth no kingdome, no glory; nothing but confuſion and ſhame, but ſorrow and paine, becauſe thou haſt liued without God, and art for euer dead to him.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Now it enamoureth euery mans affection and mind to haue God to walke with him; euery man will pretend a deſire to haue it ſo, and a hope that it is ſo. But that wee may not deceiue our ſelues, we are diligently to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vpon what condition it is that God yeeldeth himſelfe to walke with vs, and to continue with vs when he hath begun. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the Prophet telleth vs is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with God, who will by no meanes condeſcend to walke
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:654:21"/> with vs, vnleſſe we haue care to accord and agree with him. And what is our agreement with God, but our agreement with the word of God, by which he is preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſts vs, and by the fame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth himſelfe vnto vs. <note n="g" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guſt d verb. dom. ſer. 1.</note> 
               <hi>If thou ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> faith Saint <hi>Auſtin, the word of God is thine aduerſarie;</hi> and how canſt thou be ſayd to agree with God, when thou art at variance with Gods word? As touching this point, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> notably well inſtructeth vs; <note n="h" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>God is light and in him is no darkneſſe at all; if we ſay that we haue fellowſhip with him and walke in darkneſse, we lie, and the truth is not in vs; but if we walke in the light, as he is in the light</hi> (which what is it elſe but to agree with him?) <hi>then we haue fellowſhip one with another</hi> (he with vs and we with him) <hi>and the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne clenſeth vs from all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:654:21"/> our ſinnes.</hi> More particularly to expreſſe what it is to walke in the light, and to agree with God, it is ſayd vnto vs; <note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 5. 48</note> 
               <hi>be ye perfect as your heauenly father is perfect;</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 6. 36</note> 
               <hi>be yee mercifull as your heauenly father is mercifull:</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 1</note> 
               <hi>be ye followers of God as deere children and walke in loue euen as Chriſt hath loued vs:</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>as he which hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of conuerſation, as it is written,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Leuit. 11. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy.</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 3</note> 
               <hi>Euery one that hath this hope, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelfe euen as he is pure.</hi> On the other ſide, <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe?</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Paul; What communion hath light with darknes? what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? &amp;c. Wherefore come out from amongſt them, and ſeparate your ſelues, ſayth the Lord; and touch no vncleane thing, and I well receiue you, and I will be a father vnto you, and yee ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:654:22"/> be my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord almightie.</hi> This is our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and agreement with God; he is cleane, and therefore will not haue vs to touch any vncleane thing. What ſhall we ſay then of thoſe parti-colored Chriſtians and worſhippers of God, who will be one where cleane and another where vncleane; who haue faire faces and foule feete; who on the one ſide ſhake hands with God, and on the other ſide with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; yea lift vp the left hand to praye to God, and throwe ſtones at him with the right hand: who pretend by faith to knowe God, &amp; by their works deny him; who offer vnto Chriſt a ſponge of hollow profeſſion, and giue him therein to drinke the vinegre of euill conuerſation; who as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayth, <note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Worſhip God for the world to come, and the Diuell for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:654:22"/> this preſent world?</hi> They go about a thing impoſſible; to ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe things which can by no meanes ſtand together, heauen and hell, God and the Diuell, Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> true faith and wicked life. What; <hi>can two walke together except they be agreed?</hi> Can there be true faith to ſaluation where there is that life to which God hath certainly threatned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? can there be one foote in heauen with God when the other foote is with the Diuell in hell? Let no man deceiue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; either let him make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a whole burnt offering to the Lord as well in workes as in faith; as well in conuerſation as in religion, or elſe God will whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiect him: hee agreeth not with God, and therefore God will haue no company or fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:654:23"/>10 It remaineth now to ſpeake of humane ſocietie wherein wee <hi>walke together</hi> one with another, according to thoſe diuerſe bonds of coniunction wherewith God hath tied vs to be reſpectiue each to other. To which ſocietie God hath ſo framed the nature &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of man, as that concerning temporall life, it were better for a man not to be at all, then to be alone. Of the benefit whereof <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> inſtructeth vs, when he ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. 9</note> 
               <hi>Two are better then one, for they haue better wages for their labour, &amp; if they fall, the one will lift vp his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; but wo to him that is alone, for he falleth and there is not a ſecond to lift him vp: alſo if two ſleepe togither, there ſhalbe warmth, but to one how ſhould there be warmth? and if one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome him, two ſhall stand againſt him, and a threefold coard is not eaſily broken.</hi> In which words he giueth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:654:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs to vnderſtand, that whether we reſpect commoditie for wealth, or help for weaknes, or comfort for cheriſhment, or defence againſt viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, all theſe benefits are yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs by ſocietie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; but being alone are bereft of all. <hi>Ratio &amp; oratio, reaſon and ſpeech,</hi> which are the two things wherby the nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo much excelleth all the creatures of the world, what vſe haue they, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally our ſpeech, if wee haue none with whom to reaſon, &amp; to whom to ſpeake? Thoſe excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of prudence, patience, iuſtice mercy, fortitude and the reſt, what do they ſerue for, if there bee not ſociety of life for the emploiment thereof? yea the rule of chriſtian life which is directed vnto vs from God, wherein ſtandeth it for the moſt part but in precepts of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and loue, and of yeilding help
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:654:24"/> &amp; comfort each to other? So doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> inſtruct vs, <note n="ſ" place="margin">Phil. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Looke not euery man on his owne things, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man alſo on the things of other men,</hi> and hereof propoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for an example, <note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Euen as I pleaſe all men in all things, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mine owne profit, but the profit of many that they may be ſaued.</hi> Thus againe he teacheth vs; <note n="u" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Exhort one another and edify one another, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them that are vnruly, comfort the feeble minded, beare with the weake, be patient towards all men.</hi> So doth the Author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes: <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 10. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs conſider one another to prouoke vnto loue and to good workes, not forſaking the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip that wee haue amongſt our ſelues, but let vs exhort one another,</hi> &amp;c. And thus we ſee in the goſpel that our Sauiour Chriſt at the laſt day ſhall ſpecially recount thoſe good workes of charitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:654:24"/> the vſe whereof is in the ſocietie of men, and which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſociety haue no place; <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 25. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I was hungry and ye gaue me to eate, I was thirſty and ye gaue me drinke, I was naked and ye clothed me,</hi> &amp;c. Thus is ſociall life commended vnto vs as the fitteſt courſe wherin to beſtow our ſelues that we may come to God.</p>
            <p n="11">11 The more may wee wonder that ſo many, ſo great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue bin poſſeſſed with that ſuperſtitious admiration of eremiticall and ſolitarie life, as the only diuine &amp; heauenly ſtate; by which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they forſooke the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip which the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth, &amp; withdrew themſelues from thoſe good offices and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which God requireth to bee performed to other men. As if
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:654:25"/> they were wiſer then God in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining to themſelues a more excellent kinde of life then that which God had commended in the exerciſe of brotherly loue. As if they were better then the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, the Prophets, the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, the Apoſtles, who all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the ſocietie and frequency of the Church. As if it ſhould be a good anſwer vnto Chriſt at that day to ſay; Lord we haue not done thoſe workes which thou ſpeakeſt of, but left the ſame as fitting men of more weake &amp; vnperfect ſtate, and went our ſelues into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes where wee could do good to none, but onely afflicted our ſelues, and <note n="z" place="margin">Col. 2. 23</note> 
               <hi>ſpared not our bodies</hi> by watching, &amp; faſting, and lying on the ground. What we had, we left it at once, &amp; vowed neuer to haue any thing againe, ſo that though thou ſhouldeſt ſtarue for hunger
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:654:25"/> and thirſt, or periſh for cold, yet we would thenceforth haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to releiue or ſuccour thee, <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 25. 15.</note>, <hi>Talents thou gaueſt vs, but we lapped them vp and digged them into the ground, helping no man therewith ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word or deede.</hi> Behold thou haſt thine owne againe &amp; ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, but more then that wee haue gained nothing. How well this anſwere ſhall pleaſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, it reſteth for them to conſider whom it ſhall concerne; to vs it ſeemeth much vnfitting to that duety of life which Chriſt hath commended to vs.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Now in diſcourſe of humane ſocieties that is firſt and chiefly to be conſidered to which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion leadeth vs, the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety betwixt the husband and the wife, which as it is the roote and foundation of all the reſt, moſt neere &amp; ſtrait in bond, moſt loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:654:26"/> in pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, moſt commodious in benefit and vſe; ſo ſpecially ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in holy ſcriptures to deſcribe and ſet forth that coniunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement whereof the words of the Prophet are referred in this place, for nothing is there more vſuall in holy ſcripture then by termes of mariage to note the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and bond of amitie which is betwixt God and vs; God making himſelfe the bridegroome; his church and people the ſpouſe and bride, and accuſing vs as of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and fornication when our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectios are withdrawne from him and beſtowed otherwhere. The reaſon of the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie betwixt man and wife, God himſelfe deliuered in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 2. 18</note> 
               <hi>It is not good for man to bee alone, let vs make him a helper meete for him.</hi> Therfore doth hee make
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:654:26"/> him <hi>a helper,</hi> becauſe <hi>it is not good,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the man be himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone;</hi> it is good for him to haue a helper like vnto himſelfe and to be at hand with him. It is true indeed that accidentally by ſinne the caſe of mariage is much changed, and many cares and encumbrances &amp; diſtractions are incident to mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eſtate. For the auoiding wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that a man may enioy himſelfe wholly to himſelfe and ſo to God, the Apoſtle ſaith, <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 1</note> 
               <hi>It is good for a man not to touch a woman;</hi> as alſo of the woman that, <note n="d" place="margin">Verſe. 40.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe is more bleſſed if ſhe continue alone:</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when by the gift of God they haue power ouer themſelues to conteine themſelues. But if wee reſpect the ſtate of innocencie before the fall of man, or if wee reſpect the caſe of incontinencie which ſince that fall like a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deluge hath ouerflowed the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:654:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> whole nature of mankind, &amp; from whence much greater and worſe diſtraction ariſeth then from the troubles of maried eſtate, in both theſe reſpects, to both which wee doubt not but the ſentence of god hath reference, the ſame ſentence ſtandeth good; <hi>It is not good for man to be alone:</hi> it is beſt for him to haue a helper like vnto himſelfe and neere vnto him, and as it were another ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="13">13 The maner of the making of this <hi>helper</hi> is to be obſerued, which <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribeth thus, that <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 2. 21</note>, <hi>GOD ſent vpon Adam a heauie ſleepe, and in his ſleepe tooke one of his ribs out of his ſide, and cloſed it vp againe with fleſh, and of the ſame rib created the woman, and brought her to the man</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt de bono coniug cap. 1.</note>. <hi>By the ſide,</hi> ſaith Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, <hi>he ſignified the effectualnes of this coniunction, for they are ioined ſide to ſide who walke together, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:654:27"/> both together looke to one end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they walke.</hi> Vpon this framing of the woman the man pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, <hi>This is now fleſh of my fleſh &amp; bone of my bone: ſhe ſhall bee called</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>iſhah, woman, becauſe ſhe was taken out of</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>iſh, the man: for this cauſe ſhall a man leaue his father and mother, and ſhall cleaue to his wife, &amp; they two ſhall be one fleſh</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Sauiour Chriſt inferreth in the goſpell, <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 19. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore they are no more two but one fleſh: let not man therfore put aſunder that which God hath coupled together.</hi> By the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which vnſeparable vnion, our Sauiour giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the breach and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt the husband and the wife, becauſe they are but one fleſh, is a thing as vnnaturall as is the renting and ſundring of one member of the bodie from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This cannot bee in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:654:28"/> without paine and griefe: if it be in wedlock without paine, yet is it not without wound, and the wound is ſo much the more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and dangerous, by how much the leſſe it appeareth to bee a wound, and no paine is felt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Phyſitians ſay, <note n="h" place="margin">Curaeus de ſenſib. lib. 2. cap. 43. ex Galeno.</note> 
               <hi>Dolor eſt ſolutio continui: paine is the parting and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of that which hath continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and is ſubſtantially compacted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> Here is a continuation of one fleſh, &amp; if in the rupture &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be no pain, it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that either the one ſide or the other or both are but dead fleſh, &amp; without ſenſe, and therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the cauterie of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to cut them off that no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infection may thence grow.</p>
            <p n="14">14 To this bond of nature God hath alſo added a bond of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and promiſe, whereby the huſband and the wife do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:654:28"/> and vowe before God and his Church to walke together, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly to maintaine that ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to which each with other they commit themſelues. The breach of which couenant GOD repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth as a hainous treſpaſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning it one where in the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <note n="i" place="margin">Malac. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is witnes betweene thee and the wife of thy youth, againſt whom thou tranſgreſſest, who yet is thy companion &amp; the wife of thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> Another where in the wife, <note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 2. 17.</note> 
               <hi>which forſaketh the guid of her youth and forgetteth the couenant of her God;</hi> calling it <hi>the couenant of God,</hi> becauſe God is the author &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, in his name it is made, &amp; he ſhall require the performance of it. Nature, religion, fidelity, ciuility, equitie, all cry it out that the husband and the wife ſhould walke together; and yet the cry of all theſe auaileth not, but that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:654:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> ruptures and diuiſions betwixt husband and wife are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where to bee ſeene amongſt vs, ſpecially amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt men of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place, yea ſo common in many places as if it were a thing out of faſhion for great men and their wiues to liue &amp; to walke together. What great inconueniences and miſchiefs hereof enſue, it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, the ruine of houſes, extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of naturall affections both in parents and children, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipation of patrimony and ſtate, both perill and practiſe of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie and vncleanneſſe of life of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue and odious both to God and men.</p>
            <p n="15">15 For the preuenting of which miſchiefes and of that ſeparation which is the cauſe of them, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie it is for them that are to walk together to agree together, &amp; the conſcience of that bond where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:654:29"/> they are ioined as in one yoke to draw together, muſt moue them to all regard and care ſo to cary themſelues each to other, as that there may be accord &amp; peace betwixt them. Otherwiſe if they be yokefellowes &amp; agree not, but one draw one way and another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, what doe they but gall the necks and breake the hearts one of another? what is the husband in this caſe but a tyrant to his wife? what is the wife to the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d but according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ribbe whereof ſhee was made, a crooked rib: in ſtead of a help a hurt: in ſtead of a woman a wound and a wo to man. The ſcripture telleth vs that GOD is the <note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 13. 20.</note> 
               <hi>God of peace,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Cor. 14. 33.</note> 
               <hi>not the author of confuſion but of peace,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 68. 6. <hi>vulgat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them to be of one mind that dwell in a houſe.</hi> If the worke of God be peace, if he make them of one
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:654:30"/> minde that are in a houſe, what ſhall we ſay of them who vnmake that which God hath made, and maintaine war in ſtead of peace? what doe they but deſtroy the worke of god and turne him out of dores that hee may haue no place to dwell with them? we read that when God would ſpeake to <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet, there <note n="o" place="margin">1. King. 19. 11.</note> 
               <hi>went before the LORD a mightie ſtrong winde which rent the mountaines and brake the rockes, but the Lord was not in the wind: and after the winde, came an earthquake, but the Lord was not in the earthquake: &amp; after the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake came fire, but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the fire came a ſoft ſtill voice,</hi> and therin the Lord ſpake. Euen ſo is it in this caſe, where in a houſe there are the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous and ſtormy winds, the earthquakes and raging fires of brawles and contentions, of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:654:30"/> and vnquietnes, the Lord is not there: the Lord is in the ſoft and ſtill and louely voice betwixt the husband and the wife.</p>
            <p>For the preſeruing of this concord and peace betwixt man and wife, there are three things ſpecially to bee required; religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, affection, and patience. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion deliuereth the precepts of walking together; affection practiſeth them; patience remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thoſe ſtumbling blockes which befall in the way to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting and weakening both of religion and affection. Religion and the feare of God as it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the foundation of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane happineſſe and felicity, ſo muſt it in ſpeciall bee accounted the ground of all that comfort and bliſſe which man and wife de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to find in the enioying each of other. It hath ſpeciall promiſes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:654:31"/> made vnto it by God: to the man, <note n="p" place="margin">pſa. 112. 1</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, that hath great delight in his commandements:</hi> to the woman; <note n="q" place="margin">pro. 31. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Fauour is deceitfull and beauty is vanitie</hi> (a fit of an ague ſtaineth it; time decayeth it; old age weareth it quite out) <hi>but the woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 8</note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is profitable for all things, and hath the promiſes both of this life and of that that is to come.</hi> They therefore whom it concerneth to walke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, both for the things of this life, and for the obtaining of the life to come, muſt learne to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 6</note> 
               <hi>godlineſſe great gaine,</hi> and then thinke they thriue beſt when amidſt their worldly thrift they beſt thriue in religion towards God. The feare of God worketh that <note n="t" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 4</note> 
               <hi>meeke and quiet ſpirit,</hi> which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> commendeth, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:654:31"/> namely in the wife, which as it is <hi>a thing with God much ſet by,</hi> ſo it is a thing louely and amiable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, and betwixt maried perſons yeeldeth that content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſweetneſſe that holdeth them from repenting of that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety which is become ſo ioyous and comfortable vnto them. It is a prety obſeruation which <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aben Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in prou. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7 apud Pag nin. in Lexic. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> a Iewiſh Rabbine giueth of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew words before mentioned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>iſh, the man or the husband,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>iſhah; the woman or the wife,</hi> that there is contained in them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Iah,</hi> which is the name of God, the letters and vowels whereof being taken out, there remaineth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be made of the reſt but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>eſh,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>eſh,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>fire.</hi> Whereby hee would giue to vnderſtand, that if God be not betwixt the husband and the wife, if there be not in them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:654:32"/> the feare of God and conſcience of duty towards him, nothing can bee expected betwixt them but fire and fire, fire of debate and ſtrife, fire of vexation and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, fire of Gods curſe conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and waſting both them and theirs. But if God bee in their hearts; if they haue in them the feare of God, howſoeuer there may be ſometimes vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons offence and anger, yet farre is it off from danger of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and there is paine till the breach be repaired and healed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Religion preſcribeth to husband and wife the bounds, within which they are to walke each with other; the duties which they are to performe one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the preſeruing of that peace and agreement which God requireth. It ſetteth foorth <note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:654:32"/> husband to be the wiues head;</hi> not onely to import that he is to be her director and <note n="y" place="margin">Pro. 2. 17.</note> 
               <hi>guide</hi> as the head is of the body, but as the head in naturall compaſſion and loue ſtoopeth and inclineth it ſelfe to the debilities and weakneſſes of the meaneſt part of the body, and vſeth the tongue to aske, and the eare to heare, and the eye to looke for the eaſing and helping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and though he cannot preuaile for the curing of it, yet doth not in mad furie torment his owne fleſh, nor aggrauateth or exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth the maladie, but ſtill che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth the part, and maketh the beſt of all; ſo and much more ought the husband to yeelde the ſame affection and honour to his wife, to apply the vnderſtanding and diſcretion that God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed him with aboue his wife, to the couering and hiding of her
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:654:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> imperfections and infirmities, alwayes to make the beſt of them, and either medicinally to cure them, if it may be, or with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to beare what hee cannot cure; conſidering alwayes his wife to be made, not of the baſeſt or vileſt parts, as if ſhe were to be reputed or intreated like his vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall or ſlaue (euen the very heathen man accounting it <note n="z" place="margin">Bodin de repub. lib. 1 cap. 3. ex Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone.</note> 
               <hi>a point of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for a man to ſtrike his wife</hi>) but of a part neereſt to his heart, and therefore that ſhee hath ſtill right aboue all other to challenge a place there. On the other ſide it teacheth the wife to remember her ſelfe, as not made of the foot to be troden vpon, ſo neither of the head to be as a maſter or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, but of the ſide; and though as a companion, yet an inferior to her husband; and therefore that ſhe ought <note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5. 22</note> 
               <hi>to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:654:33"/> her ſelfe to her husband,</hi> that <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>her deſire is to be ſubiect vnto him, and he is to rule ouer her, that</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe is not to vſurpe authoritie ouer her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, but</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 14 34.</note> 
               <hi>to be in ſubiection as the lawe teacheth.</hi> It teacheth huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands <note n="e" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 7</note> 
               <hi>to dwell diſcreetly with their wiues, giuing honour to the wife as vnto the weaker veſsell, euen as they who are heires together with them of the grace of life.</hi> Againe it teacheth the wife to be <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 2. 18.</note> 
               <hi>a helper to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> as was ſaid before, and not a hinderer, <note n="g" place="margin">Eccleſ. 36. 24.</note> 
               <hi>a pillar for him to reſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon,</hi> not a ſtumbling block to make him fall: <note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 12. 4</note> 
               <hi>the glory of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> not an infamy and reproch to him; a meanes <note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 1</note> 
               <hi>to winne him by her good conuerſation, if he do not yet obey the word,</hi> not an occaſion to offend him and driue him further off from the liking of the word. It teacheth <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 33. 44.</note> 
               <hi>the huſband in the things of the world to care how hee may
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:654:34"/> pleaſe his wife; and the wife likewiſe in the ſame to care how ſhe may pleaſe her huſband.</hi> In a word, it teacheth both husband &amp; wife to ſet God before their eies, and to conſider mariage as his ordinance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and that to him they ſhall giue account how they haue vſed it with that honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard which he hath required as due vnto it.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Which that it may be the more duely performed, neceſſary it is that with religion there be ioyned <hi>affection,</hi> and without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection religion ſufficeth not. Affection, I ſay, whereby each is entertained and lodged in the heart of other, and do yeeld each to other that contentment and delight as that it may bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith; <note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 5. 18</note> 
               <hi>Reioyce with the wife of thy youth, let her bee vnto thee as the louing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:654:34"/> Hinde, and as the pleaſant Roe, let her breaſtes alwayes ſatisfie thee, and delight thou in her loue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi> It is very worthy to be noted how the holy Ghoſt in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles to deſcribe the amitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and his Church, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaneth himſelfe to the phraſes of amitie betwixt the husband &amp; the wife, <note n="m" place="margin">Cant. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. &amp; 4 10. &amp; 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>my faire one, my ſiſter, my ſpouſe, my loue, my doue, my vndefiled,</hi> and ſuch like, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and ſanctifie the ſame to the vſe of chaſte and faithful loue, ſo to import what the affection ought to bee, which is to vtter it ſelfe by the iſſues and ſtreames of ſuch gratious and louely wordes. It was truly ſaid by him that ſaid it, that <note n="n" place="margin">Bodin. <hi>de repub. lib: 1. cap. 3. ex Artemidore.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>marriage loue ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede and ouerpaſſe all other kindes of amitie and loue:</hi> and therefore the foundations of mariage are to be laid accordingly, that affection
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:654:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> truly and faithfully obteined on both parts may be thenceforth as an impregnable fortreſſe &amp; caſtle neuer to bee conquered or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. Therefore raſh and haſty and caſuall marriages are to bee condemned, wherin their wanteth time and occaſion, and meanes to linck together the hearts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of them that are to liue together, and that barbarous and wicked cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell is followed which ſometimes is giuen, to marrie firſt and to loue after. Whereby it commeth to paſſe that marriages many times are but diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and draw after them a long cord of miſerie and ſorrowe and grieuance of the one party againſt the other, and both aduiſedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of that which they vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly begun. Of the ſame kind are thoſe marriages which <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaketh of whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men make choice
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:654:35"/> of wiues, <note n="o" place="margin">Hieron. idu. Iouini au. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>non oculis ſed digitis, not by their eies but by their fingers,</hi> not by their eies by which the perſon and behauiour is diſcerned &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, but by the fingers by which the money is told, that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being reſpected how rich ſhe is in the purſe, not how well to bee liked in her ſelfe, the man many times by this occaſion thinking that he hath a good marriage if the woman were away, and the woman by like occaſion think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelfe well married if the husband were away, and the one hoping and wiſhing ſoone, the ſooner the better, to bee rid of the other. Laſciuious and wanton eies are indeed greatly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; but yet in honeſt and lawfull loue the eie is the window by which affection and loue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the heart, and if the eie beare not ſome ſtroke in choice of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:654:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> a companion to liue ſo neerely with, ſo as that the huſband be to the wife, <note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 20. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the vaile of her eies</hi> to ſtay her from looking to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the wife to the husband, <note n="q" place="margin">Ezech. 24. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the pleaſure of his eies,</hi> that hee may ioy to behold her, ill is that mariage ſorted, and whatſoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contentments there may bee in it, there wanteth that which ſhould be the ſeaſoning &amp; ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all the reſt.</p>
            <p n="19">19 From religion and affection muſt grow <hi>patience</hi> both in huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife, whereby vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of heare and anger, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which hardly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our life paſſe, each can kindly beare with other; and each is carefull to take that notice and knowledge of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſition of the other as may ſerue to preuent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thoſe vncomely extremities to which intemperate and vnbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:654:36"/> fury carieth headlong both one and other. Wee are all fleſh and bloud, we all haue our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and ouerſights; but pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and loue digeſteth all, and ſtill healeth that which offence woundeth. But if there be no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; if by impatiencie the one be fire and the other flax and gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, what muſt needs followe but the blowing vp and burning of the whole houſe? To be ſhort, <note n="r" place="margin">Eccl. 25. 1.</note> 
               <hi>three things are there,</hi> ſaith the ſon of Syrach, <hi>which reioice mee, and whereby I am beautified both before God and men, the vnitie of brethren, the loue of neighbours, and a man and wife that agree together.</hi> The more gratious &amp; gladſome theſe things are, and namely the amitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the husband and the wife, ſo much the more it concerneth all partes to vſe all care for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of amitie and vnitie as a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:654:37"/> iewell moſt pretious in the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and acceptation both of God and men.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Now here I might further ſpeake of the other two, the vnity of brethren, the loue of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and generally of peace and concord, as the garland &amp; crown of heauen, the glory of the earth, the ſtrength of kingdoms, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of families, the ioy and happines of all ſocieties, the light of all mens eies, and the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of all mens bones; as on the other ſide diſcord and variance to be vncapable of heauen, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the earth, the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of kingdomes, the ouerthrow of families, the bane of all ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as thornes in all mens ſides, and as fire in the bones of all men. But I haue already ſtood long, and therefore will here end, leauing the reſt to be vnderſtood by that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:654:37"/> that I haue ſayde. &amp;c. <hi>To God the Father, God the Sonne, God the holy ghoſt bee all honour and Glory for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
